<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lazarus his rest preached in a sermon at the funerall of Mr. Ephraim Udall, that famous divine in London / by Tho. Reeve ...</title>
            <author>Reeve, Thomas, 1594-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R691A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10612</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12827353</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12827353</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94287</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58346)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94287)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 776:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lazarus his rest preached in a sermon at the funerall of Mr. Ephraim Udall, that famous divine in London / by Tho. Reeve ...</title>
                  <author>Reeve, Thomas, 1594-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 [i.e. 30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Moseley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Udall, Ephraim, d. 1647.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94287:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94287:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LAZARUS HIS REST. Preached in a Sermon at the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of Mr. <hi>Ephraim Udall,</hi> that famous Divine in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THO. REEVE, <hi>Bachelor in Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Paſtor ac pauper hac ſunt homini Chriſtiano ornamenta — Mox ventilabrunt adeſt paleas ſecerint à frumento, &amp; quod leve eſt, &amp; inſtabile ſejungit ab eo, quod alendi vim habet — Non vereor accedere veretati non ſum ad ſycophantiam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Baſil. hom, 26. de Martyre mamante.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Fugit ſicut Loth, qui renuntiat viros, abdicat ſe incolarum mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, qui poſt ſe non reſpicit,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Amb. l. de fugae ſaeculi. c. 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Nec enim ſaltem attingere debet praeclari hujus muneris functio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, niſi paratus ſit millies animam ſuam in mortem tradere,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jo. Chryſ. de laudibus D. Pauli. hom. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>H. Moſeley,</hi> at the ſigne of the Princes Armes in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94287:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94287:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Lazarus his Reſt.</hi> Preached in a Sermon at the Funerall of Mr. <hi>Ephraim Vdall,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Retious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints. Death in it ſelf is hideous,<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.15.</note> but conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Saints, pretious; it is ſo in Gods ſight, and ſhall it not in mens? Yes we ſhould looke upon ſuch occaſions with Gods eye, ſee as he ſee, prize as he prize; not make that death wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he maketh bleſſed; nor that vile that he makes pretious, for a pretious Saint makes a pretious death. <hi>Preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such a Saint I am now to preſent unto you, in whom we ſee ſcarce any infirmity but that of nature, or little other ſcarre then that of the grave; Death might unskin him, but it could not un-Saint him: no, he is the leſſe man for death, but not the leſſe Saint;<note place="margin">—Vivit poſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>era virtus.</note> he was a timely Saint, and therefore not a Saint to be untimed, he was a Saint in life, a ſaint in death, therefore a ſaint after death; we may bury the man, but we cannot the ſaint; no, in this he remains ſtill vigorous, ſtill pretious, <hi>Pretious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his ſaints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And well may I ſay pretious, I ſay not, what urn had in it more pretious aſhes? but what ſhrine hath had in it more ſacred duſt? There is a religion that talketh much of their ſaints working mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but here is one that wrought the true miracles; he cured diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, even the diſeaſes of corrupt nature, and drove away Devils, even Legions that came to poſſeſſe him; when he entred into the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſearch of himſelf, he could ſpie out nothing but humane frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; Pray (Sir) ſaid he I beſeech you, for the forgiveneſſe of my ſins I mean my humane frailties, no other thing, I praiſe God doth bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then me. O cleanſed piece that had nothing in him but that ſoy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94287:3"/>that concupiſcence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>ineth us withall! for beſides that hereditary poyſon,<note place="margin">Virus paternum <hi>Aug.</hi> Peccata ſurrep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis: <hi>Aug.</hi> Peccata quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianae incurſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. <hi>Tertull.</hi> Abraſa ſpurci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laris. <hi>Bern.</hi> In mundo ſupra mundumeſſe. <hi>Amb.</hi> Sanctitas mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiem ſignificat <hi>Aquin. Zach. 9.7. Dan, 12.10. Heb. 10.22. Rev. 3.4.</hi>
                  </note> and a few ſwellings, I mean inordinate motions, frail weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and ſudden paſſions, ſinnes of ſurreption, and daily incurſion, he could diſcern no venome in him; a man he was, but one that had as little of man as could be imagined; unleſſe therefore ye would have had him never to have been skinned in our nature, what leſſer imperfections could ye have wiſhed to have been in him? no, a ſaint he was becauſe he had ſo little entireneſſe with the fleſh; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the filth of wordly retriment was taken out of him, becauſe he did learn in the world to be above the world. If ſanctity ſignifie cleanneſſe, then what a rinſed creature have we here?</p>
               <p>Envy it ſelf cannot put him amongſt the ſpots of the times, no, one he was that might ſtand amongſt them, which had the blood ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of their mouths; amongſt them which were purified, and made white, amongſt them which had waſhed their bodies with pure water; amongſt them, which had not defiled their garments, his whole life being nothing but a ſtudy of ſelf denyall, and a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of mortification; he was no drunkard, no adulterer, no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſour.</p>
               <p n="1">1 No drunkard, his temperance ſuch, that he ſcarce ever knew an intemperate draught, or drank to ſatisfie delight; that whereas he lived in the midſt of a riotous age wholy given up to exceſſe (for this is a new kind of meaſure where men drink beyond meaſure,<note place="margin">Novum hoc menſurae genus, ubi nullus eſt menſurae modus <hi>Amb.</hi> Vaſa vinaria. <hi>Baſil.</hi> Caſtitas eſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſub jugo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis impetum libidinis refrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans, <hi>Aug.</hi> Si cingulo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitatis careas, omnia per ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram trahes. <hi>Ierom.</hi>
                  </note> men ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſing ſo long till they ſmell above ground, and ſeem to be nothing elſe but wine casks) he ſeemed to be born to pluck the quaffing cup from the mouths of Boon fellows, and to teach the world ſobriety.</p>
               <p n="2">2 No adulterer, his chaſtity was ſuch, that he did keep that wild beaſt of luſt under a yoke, he kept his garments from drabling by tying them up, by the girdle of continency, he never knew any ſtrange fleſh; no, he betrothed his affections to one, and as he loved her dearly, ſo he loved her only. That whereas many walk the ſtreets to meet with an unclean ſpirit, and diſſolve the bands of marriage as eaſily as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did his green cords; theſe bands to him were ſacred and inviolable, he never deſired to have them untwiſted; he poſſeſſed his veſſell in holineſſe, and honour, he might ſtand forth as a mirrour of chaſtity.<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 He was no oppreſſour, his juſtice ſuch that he never pinched for meanes, nor fetched in the world with the dragge take; no, he had
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94287:3"/>rather content himſelf with food convenient, then raiſe his flanks by feeding upon other mens rights;<note place="margin">Divitem vell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fieri de exigui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate mendici <hi>Caſſiodor.</hi> Incommode commodum augere. <hi>Cicero.</hi>
                  </note> he never liked that eſtate that was wreſted from the poores pittance, or that came weeping home with the teares of the oppreſſed in it, no, he would not by dammage raiſe advantage. That whereas in this gripple extort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing age, men care not what key they uſe, ſo it will but unlock the doore, or what hook they bait, ſo it will but draw up lucre; great they will be, though it be with the curſes of multitudes, poſſeſſe they will, though it be with an <hi>Ahabs</hi> evidence; he on the other ſide kept his hands clean from all theſe unjuſt gains,<note place="margin">Micah. 2.2.</note> he did never oppreſſe a man, and his houſe, a man and his heritage.</p>
               <p>What ſhould I ſpeak further of any vicious courſes that this world is deeply criminall in? he was touched with no groſse ſin; no, a Saint he was becauſe he carried a crucified heart to all that which the world calls contentment; he was one that had paſsed through the refiners fire, and that had the fullers nitre ſeen upon him, a Saint he was to the world, and a Saint no doubt he is to God for his unſpotted converſation, yea queſtionles even for his purity, he is amongſt thoſe Armies of heaven, which follow the Lambe upon the white horſes, cloathed in fine liynen, white,<note place="margin">Rev. 19.14.</note> and clean.</p>
               <p>But this ye will ſay is all but mortification, had he nothing in him of vivification? yes he was enlivened with the moſt quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning powers of the Spirit; his loyns were not onely girt up, but his lamp was burning, a Saint he was for the moſt ſaintly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>How many ſingular graces and conſpicuous vertues had he in him? I will not inſiſt upon all. I will mention a few; he was humble, he was peaceable, he was charitable, he was devour, he was ſincere.</p>
               <p n="1">1 He was humble, of no haughty, inſolent demeanour, but the meekned creature of his times,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1 Pet. 5.5.</hi> Cogitas mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam conſlituere fabricam Celſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis? de funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento prius co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gita humilitatis <hi>Aug. Pſal. 131.2.</hi>
                  </note> one of the gentleſt perſons that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver trod your ſtreets, a man cloathed with humility; being to raiſe a great fabrick, he be thought himſelf of a low foundation, his affections ſo ſoft, that his ſoule was even as a weaned child, of a ſweet, affable, courteous diſpoſition, familiar with the meaneſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Peaceable, the well tuned ſtring of the inſtrument, the calm ſtream of Profeſſion, he knew that to live in unity was to live an
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94287:4"/>Angelicall life,<note place="margin">Nec inveniri poteſt forma ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſior conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſationis Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae; quam uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ſocialis. <hi>Caffiodor. Ezech. 28.24. Num. 12.3.</hi> Tu nimium one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us es, da, &amp; pondus minuis <hi>Aug. Neh. 8.10.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am tuam colloca ubi patriam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes. <hi>Chriſ. Iob. 29.25.</hi>
                  </note> therefore he compoſed his ſpirit to his heavenly temper, he never diſquieted the age with contentions, nor vexed his Pariſh with ſuits, but made more uſe of his buckler then his ſword, patience then revenge, no pricking brier or grieving thorn, but very meek above all the men upon earth.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Charitable, ſo long as he enjoyed meanes, he thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf over burthened, till he had lightened himſelf with almes deeds he had no lither arm, for he did ſtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch out his hand to the need; he fed not himſelf onely out of his meanes, but he did ſend porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to them, for whom none was provided, he loved to have a ſtock going in his right country. The riches of his liberality 2. Cor. 8.2. is ſufficiently known to you all, he delighted to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Job, even as one that comforieth the mourners.</hi> How many taſled of his liberall ſpirit? yea how many might even have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed if they had not been ſuſteined by the vertue of his charity?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Devout, not one that upheld a profeſſion wherein there was nothing to be ſeen, but the phantaſme of Religion; not one of <hi>Thriverus</hi> his needle work flowers, which are more for ſhew then ſmell,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phantaſma re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis</hi> Gorg. Rom. 12.12.</note> but a man that glowed towards his God, and was fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in the ſpirit; much time he ſpent in meditation, much in prayer, he was the blown coal of zeale, the bright flame of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Sincere, that is but a thickbrained ſtrictneſſe, that hath not in it ſimplicity, therefore out deare brother ſaid he liked alwayes in matter of Religion clearneſſe of ſpirit;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stulta rectitudo ſine ſimplicitate.</hi> Beda. Epheſ. 6.5. 1 Tim. 1.5.</note> he could not double, nor comply; no what his conſcience was perſwaded of, he follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſinglenes of heart; he hated palliating of a cauſe, what he profeſſed was out of a pure heart, &amp; a good conſcience, and ſaith unſeined; he had rather eclipſe his credit, then ſuppreſſe a truth; yea ſuffer death, then be guilty of backſliding or revolting.</p>
               <p>A Saint then he was in all theſe reſpects, and by all theſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhall he not be juſtified before men? yes no doubt, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with his God; he which did thus excell in vertue is queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe now come to his true mount,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.3.</note>, God hath taken home his true Saint to himſelf,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Colloſ. 1.12.</hi> Gaudet unus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſque angelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tale onus tangere.</note> and made ſuch a bright creature a meet partaker of the inheritance of the Saints in light. Every one of the angells delighted to touch, to carry away ſuch a burthen, as Chryſ. ſayd of the ſoule of <hi>Lazarus.</hi> And the rather for his high perfections in his own calling.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94287:4"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Tunc eſt ſermo vivus &amp; effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cax, cum eſt praeditantis ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitas, &amp; vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſa perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitas. <hi>Greg.</hi>
                  </note>A Miniſter he was and what not a Saint in his own ſacred function? yes, then is the Word lively and effectuall when it is edged with the ſanctified and gracious life of the Teacher; and what an exact, accompliſhed Teacher have we here? a man that had in him the very luſtre of pietie, and ſplendour of ſanctity; few men had greater judgement, none greater integrity; he was not onely one of the walking Libraries, and ſpeaking Oracles of his age a moſt judicious, and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Preacher but a moſt gracious liver a burning and a ſhining Lampe.<note place="margin">Seipſum primo immolet, ſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum vitiis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulet, &amp; ſua prius peccato membra morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficet, <hi>Orig. l. in Epiſt. ad Rom.</hi>
                  </note> He had learned well that of <hi>Origen</hi> that the Prieſt which would ſacrifice for others muſt take heed of a ſpot in his owne oblation, he muſt firſt offer up himſelfe, kill his own perſonal vices, mortity his own unregenerate cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. For what pleaſant fruit can the people taſte out of the Pulpit, if the Miniſter himſelfe ſhould happen to bee a wild Plant? <hi>Can a man gather grapes of thornes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sermo dulcedi nem non habet, quem vita re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proba intra con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mordet, <hi>Greg. in fine Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</hi>
                  </note>That doctrine hath no ſweetneſſe, which a reprobate life cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth; no, a pure conſcience doth more edifie then curious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Therefore how ſtrict was this our deare Brother to have his life exemplary, to deliver not onely pointed ſpeeches, but to wound conſciences by the ſight of his innocent converſation? there was nothing did drop out of his lips but it ſeemed to flow from the cleere ſpring of his owne ſanctified heart; hee would not ſuffer his doctrine to be traduced by the ſcandall of his life;<note place="margin">Ad praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum plus conſcientia ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti amoris aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, quam exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatio ſermonis. <hi>Id. ſuper E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zech. hom. 10.</hi> Qui enim Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum annuntiat, ab omni vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum incentivo debet praeſtare ſe alienum. <hi>Amb. in Ser. de. je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jun.</hi>
                  </note> no, he preached nothing in the Pulpit, but he firſt preached it to himſelfe in his Cloſet, his counſell was but the counterpane of his converſation, he knew the Meſſenger of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t had need be the moſt inculpable perſon upon earth; What beneficiall thing can he do to the Church, which remaineth himſelfe a skarre among men? or what comfort can it be to any mans ſoule to renew others, and to continue himſelfe uncorrigible? No, unto the ungodly ſaid God. Why takeſt thou my covenant into thy mouth, and hateſt to be reformed? ſuch an one may ſay with the Father, I have drawne out a faire picture which exceeds the Painters beauty, and have ſet others on ſhore, being toſſing my ſelfe ſtill upon the waves of dangerous ſinnes.<note place="margin">Pulchrum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinxi hominem pictor foedus, alioſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>itus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digo, qui adhuc in delictorum fluctibus verſor. <hi>Greg. in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral.</hi>
                  </note> Therefore our Brother was carefull to have the beſt man of the pariſh beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94287:5"/>even to have his owne demeanour, a kind of tranſlated Scripture, or the great Text to his people, leſt when he had prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to others, himſelfe ſhould be found a Reprobate.</p>
               <p>The behaviour then of this our deare and reverend Brother was nothing elſe but the high proſpect of vertue; and as hee wanted not grace, ſo what wanted he elſe to make him an eminent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? I known,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.1.</note> it is required of the Diſpoſers, that every one bee found faithfull, and a faithfuller ſteward there was ſcarce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the whole family, that as he digged the gold mines for treaſure, and ſought for wiſdome as for Silver, ſo he diſperſed his Ingots with great fidelity. He laboured in the Word, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, laboured till his labours were a burthen, laboured till he was ſcarſe able to labour; yet his feeble and craſie body could not intermit his paines, but hee ſtrove with nature, and forced himſelfe beyond nature;<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15. 2 Cor. 8.23. Eſ. 62.6.</note> a diligent workman hee was, and one that needed not to be aſhamed; he was one of thoſe Meſſengers of the Churchs, that was the glory of Chriſt, a Watchman that did not hold his peace upon the walls, day nor night. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you ſaw the Evidence of the Spirit in his teaching? How many of you have the ſeale of his Miniſtry upon your conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? a multitude of loſt groates were found by the light of this Candle, many thouſand Converts have occaſion in this City to bleſſe God, that ever their eares came under his charming, that ever they ſtood within the preſence of ſuch a Paſtour according to Gods owne heart,<note place="margin">Ier. 3.</note> who did feed them with wiſdome and knowledge. A Saint then he was in the whole courſe of his life, but an eminent Saint in his Miniſtery.</p>
               <p>But if his Pulpit could not ſave him,<note place="margin">Ibin aſunt ubi conſenuit, jam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quod erat turbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum expiravit, aromatice olere, <hi>Plut. in mor.</hi> Athletae cum metam vident, &amp; accedunt propius, et ſi feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, approperant, <hi>Thriv. l. 1. c. 1. mon. &amp; exemp.</hi>
                  </note> his Death-bed did. Our <hi>Ibis</hi> having purged out of him every thing that was offenſive and ill ſavouring did at the laſt gaſpe ſmell moſt odoriferouſly, yea, like one skilfull in running of a race, when he drew nigh to the marke, he did quicken his pace. Oh how admirable were his paſſages upon his death-bed? he departed like a paſſionate Pilgrim, longing to ſet foot upon his owne Countrey. Hee did not then onely patiently endure affliction, or ſpy out Death ſapping into his walls, but hee turned himſelfe out of this world, and looked out with an aking ey to ſee his laſt Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94287:5"/>approch, he declared a lively confidence that he had of a myſticall union with God, and aſpired to have the fruition of thoſe joyes, that he had got an engagement of by faith. Here I might ſpeake much, but I am ſtrooke mute by the command of my dead Friend, he hath ſilenced me from publiſhing any thing, that paſſed between us in private concerning his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſcrutiny, his profeſſion of faith, or the experimentall grounds that he found in himſelfe of divine favour. But this I aſſute you that he died like a man ſingularly ſtudied in the deepeſt miſteries, and ſealed up his life with a moſt judicious, and firme conſent to his profeſſed principles; yea, I never met with a more Angelicall tongue, and raviſhed ſoule upon ſuch a ſolemne occaſion.</p>
               <p>His life then was admirable, but his death memorable, there he was a Saint in tranſcendency. Dead then he is, but dead to his God; dead he is, but with the death of a Saint; God and his ſaint are met, and after all the miſeries of death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what can we expect, but that which is pretious? if the world ſhould ſtill look upon him with an ey of neglect, God no doubt lookes upon him with an eye of divine favour; let him therefore be in thy ſight, as he is in Gods ſight. Oh that thou ſaweſt but the honour that is done unto him above I that thou ſaweſt but the noble entertainment which he hath received at Court! what brightneſſe did there ſhine upon him at the opening of Heaven gates! what an extaſie hath this ſoule felt by the rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Hallelujahs of Angels! the hidden Mannah is already melting in his mouth, the robe of glory is upon his back, the crowne of eternity is ſet upon his head the which ſought for wiſdome more pretious then Rubies,<note place="margin">Pro. 3.15. Prov. 20.15. Pſ. 126.6. Eccleſ. 7.1.</note> and had the lipps of knowledge which are as a precious jewell, which went forth <hi>weeping</hi> bearing his pretious <hi>ſeed</hi> with him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and left a good name behind him, better then a pretious ointment he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no doubt before this time the benefit of a pretious faith,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.1.</note> and hath felt the comfort of the great and pretious promiſes,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> he is gotten into the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 21.19.</note> whoſe foundations are garniſhed with all manner of precious ſtones, &amp; joyned to his bleſſed Redeemer, that pretious, tried, corner ſtone laid in Sion.<note place="margin">Eſ. 28.16.</note>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:94287:6"/>Oh then let us not looke ſad at his death, for it is the death of a Saint, pretious let him be in our memory, for he is pretious in Gods ſight. <hi>Pretious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Text.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jo. 11.11.</hi> Our friend Lazarus ſleepeth.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is going to <hi>Judea, v.</hi> 7. and the Diſciples thinke he is going to a ſtone heape, for <hi>the Iewes ſought lately to ſtone thee, and wilt thou goe thither againe? v.</hi> 8. No ſaith Chriſt, my intention is not for the ſtone-heape, but a duſt heape; I may goe amongſt the living, but my purpoſe is for the dead; this journey is not for my wakefull enemies, but my ſleeping Friend, <hi>Our friend Lazarus ſleepeth. Lazarus,</hi> I often viſited thee at thy houſe, I will now viſit thee at thy grave; though <hi>Iudea</hi> be a place envious, ominous, yet I will venture to the ſtone-heape, for the duſt-heapes ſake, therefore <hi>Let us goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Iudea,</hi> for it is the ſleeping couch of my Friend; <hi>Our friend Lazarus ſleepeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Text conſider</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Nature of the perſon, <hi>Our friend</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. His name <hi>Lazarus</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The accident <hi>ſleepeth.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt for the Nature of the perſon, in which two things,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. His Diſpoſition, <hi>A friend.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. His relation, <hi>Our friend.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt for his diſpoſition, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>A friend.</hi> Chriſt would goe into <hi>Iudea</hi> for <hi>a Friend.</hi> From hence obſerve that the <hi>memory of a friend ſhould be pretious,</hi> it is as the dying ring bequeathed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, that nothing but death ſhould pluck off from our fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or as a ſacred relique, that poſterity ſhould keepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violate; that when we cannot ſtand ſpectatours of our Friends, yet we ſhould ſtand Remembrancers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to recount all paſſages of worth, to preſerve their graces; for where elſe is the <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting remembrancer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.6. Prov. 10.7.</note> where the <hi>memory</hi> that ſhould be bleſſed?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94287:6"/>Is not this commended to ſurvivours to take care of? Yes, that when they ſive not, yet herein they ſhould be vitall, they ſhould have the breath of affection, for the breath in their noſtrills to continue them alive. Doth not <hi>David</hi> thus chafe the temples of his dead friend <hi>Ionathan?</hi> yes, <hi>Ionathan</hi> is gone, but <hi>Ionathan</hi> ſhall not thus part, he ſhall breath ſtill in commemoration, <hi>Woe is me, for thee my brother</hi> Jonathan <hi>very kind haſt thou been to mee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.26.</note> 
                  <hi>thy love to me was wonderfull paſſing the love of women,</hi> &amp;c. Doe not <hi>Eliſha</hi> thus call back <hi>Elias</hi> out of the cloudes? <hi>My Father, my Father the Chariots of Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and the horſmen thereof!</hi> he would not quite loſe his Father, no, <hi>my Father, my Father!</hi> he would not utterly let the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion of his Countrey go, no <hi>the Chariots of Iſrael, and the Horſemen thereof!</hi> he would have his Father ſtill in his eye, and the Kingdomes Champion dreſſed up in bright harneſſe before him. Do not the Jewes thus preſerve their good <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> ſtill alive? yes, the memory of <hi>Ioſias</hi> ſhall be like the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume of the Apothecary, and as Muſick at a banquet of wine. The ſmell of this perſume ſhall not out of their noſtrills,<note place="margin">Ecclus. 49.1.</note> the ſtreynes of this muſicke ſhall not out of their cares, the taſte of this banquet ſhall nor out of their palates, <hi>Ioſias</hi> ſhall live in memory. And this is indeed the right committing of Friends to the earth, or the maintaining of familiarity with them in their graves,<note place="margin">Non ego tumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum floribus aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pergam ſed ſpiritum ejus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore perſundam, <hi>Amb. orat. fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neb. de Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin.</hi> Olim eviſcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus es, non tam ſubito erueris, <hi>Amb. orat. fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebri de ſat.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaid of <hi>Valentinian I will not ſtrew his tombe with flowers, but I will ſprinkle his ſpirit with a ſweet odour,</hi> and this is the right enbalming of Friends; he is but a formall Friend, that parts ſo ſoone as nature parts; no, thou wert long ſince embowelled into me thou ſhall not ſo ſuddenly be taken out; ſtill he remaines, though not in ſight yet in ſenſe, ſtill he is a <hi>Friend.</hi> The uſe of this ſerves to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them which doe ſo ſoone bury their Friends, or put them ſo deepe under-ground, or lay them with their faces downwards as if being dead, they live no longer to them, the affection of the one, expectorates with the wind of the other, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> they have both breathed their laſt, <note place="margin">zach. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>quod mortuum, mortuum, that which dy let it dy.</hi> Being once dead they never pull off the darke mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter, to behold the face of their departed Friends,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94287:7"/>they commit all to the earth, even the memory, they do not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bury that which nature elſe would bury, the carcaſe, but they bury that which neither nature nor grace ſhould bury, they bury the friend, they thre away all with the grave ſpade; Priends carry nothing out of the world, nor they leave nothing in the world, not their memory; they are but of ſhort continuance, and a man may judge it by the affection of them which they have left behind them; nature ſeemed kinder to them, then ſeeming affection, for whereas nature ſuffered them to live many yeares in the world, the other not three moneths, ſcarce three minutes after their funerall, then earth to earth, one dead friend to another, a double Funerall in one day.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Quanquam ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parati ſumus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectu non ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men affectibus. <hi>Amb.</hi> Perpetuus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae debitor. <hi>Prudent.</hi> Quanquam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, attamen in nobis. Baſil.</note>But is this affection? are theſe the bands of love? ſuch a ſhort ſtint put to friendſhip? Do the pulſe ſo ſoon leave beating? Haſt not one ſparke to glow upon the grave of thy friend? yes though we be ſeparated in ſight, ye not in apprehenſion, thou muſt ſtill be a ſurety for thy friends reputation yea the perpetuall debtour of his ſpirit, to prize his name, to honour his memory, to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliſe him, to give him a reſurrection, to love him under ground as well as above ground, that though he live not with us, yet he muſt live in us, ſtill he muſt be a friend. Chriſt cannot forget his friend, no let us go to <hi>Judea</hi> for a friend.</p>
               <p>Secondly from hence obſerve that we muſt venture for a friend, let us go to <hi>Judea</hi> for a friend.<note place="margin">2 Doct.</note> It is a eaſy matter to ſay, Sir, I am wholly yours, it is the common complement of the age. He loves his friend that expoſeth himſelf to danger for him,<note place="margin">Facile eſt dicere totus ſum tuus <hi>Aug. 4. Eſter 16. Cant. 8.6.</hi> Certandi labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem non fugit. <hi>Chriſ.</hi> Incus non me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit ſtrepitum. <hi>Adag. Vſe.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Eſther</hi> for her countrymen, <hi>If I periſh,</hi> I <hi>periſh.</hi> Love is as ſtrong as death ſincere affection ſhunneth not a skirmiſh for a friend. The anvil of Love feareth not the greateſt ſtroke of envy, and oppoſition; <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan</hi> will venture to have a javelin caſt at his head for his dear friend <hi>David, Abraham</hi> will march through pikes and ſpeares, to reſcue his vowed friend <hi>Lot;</hi> we muſt jeopard for a friend, let us go to <hi>Judea</hi> for a friend. The uſe of this ſerves to reprove them which give over the venturous point, which run a way from the ſtone heap; though hands be never ſo faſtly joyned together, yet if perill be threatned, they uncloſe, pull back, withdraw, there is neither hand nor heart then left; no, let the friend then ſhift
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94287:7"/>for himſelf, if they can love a man u pon ſafe termes they will ſtand by him, but if the ſtones begin to fly,<note place="margin">Fugiunt nee noſcitur ulli. Agminibus co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitum, qui mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do cinctus erat.</note> they flee away and he is not known of any, that ſeemed before to carry the crowd at his back. Men are then weary of friendſhip, ſick of their friend, they will not come at him, look upon him, but leave him to his own chance. But oh beloved, a ſtranger an enemy might do thus much; that is but delicate friendſhip therefore, that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth onely the felicity of the friend,<note place="margin">Sive in vita, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve in morte.</note> paſſionate love like <hi>Ittai</hi> accompany a friend whether in life or death. The name of a friend, ſhould call thee out to all hazards, make thee to draw up towards him, though thy paſſage lay by the ſtoneheap. Let vs go to <hi>Judea,</hi> for a Friend.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3. Doct.</hi> Pignus naturae. <hi>Avg.</hi> Omnis cogitatio taedium, &amp; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vita peregri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio eſt. <hi>Plut. Rom. 12.18.</hi>
                  </note>Thirdly, from hence obſerve that mans honour is to be of a friendly nature, for this is the pledge of nature. Wherefore cameſt thou into the world, but to be a companion? if thou wilt not be a friend, every though is irkſomneſſe, and the Whole life a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage. What more worthy in man then humanity? and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in can humanity better be expreſſed then in friendſhip, wherefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>As much as in you lieth have peace with all men, keep the world quiet, diſtaſt no man;</hi> no,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>be ye courteous one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another,</hi> Let ſerpents ſting, men embrace; Let wild beaſts be ſavage, men be courteous. The courteous man, draweth the ſweet breath upon earth, giveth to the world the faire touch, he is the pleaſure of life, the geinme of converſation, the right hand of familiarity, the link of ſociety,<note place="margin">Dorice canere. <hi>Adag.</hi>
                  </note> he makes men ſing the <hi>Dorian</hi> tunes upon earth. <hi>Love brotherly fellowſhip</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; brotherly fellowſhip, rather brotherly commerce, brotherly fellowſhip, rather then unbrotherly frowardneſse; This brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fellowſhip is the free tenure of the pariſh, the reſt hold in vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenage, the beſt town ſtock, the reſt is but a picklock to ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the common treaſure, for a litigious perſon is the great boot haler, or harpy amongſt men,<note place="margin">1 Pet. v. 17. <hi>Sive iraſcatur, ſiverideat.</hi> Aug. Vſe.</note> whether he be angry or laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he is not to be truſted, for he is gendring of miſchiefs, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the country, and to pill the neighbourhood; a man can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſecure in his preſence, for he is no friend. The uſe of this ſerves to lament a ſad caſualty, a great misfortune is happened upon earth, the world hath loſt her friend. We live in a froward age, a troubleſome corner, the times are ſet upon jangling, how
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94287:8"/>hot ſoever the age be in ſpirituall fervour, yet it warmeth not the Nation with affection, the love of many wax cold. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a ſparkling coal there be in the Temple, yet there is but a dead aſh in the ſtreets, burning zeale doth not kindle kind reſpects amongſt men. Many men have no other ſpittle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their tongues then malice, their mouthes are furred with variances,<note place="margin">Mites ſunt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec nihil dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, vel agitur ni ſi pro eorum arbitrio, <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> they are gentle creatures, ſo long as nothing be either ſayd or done, but according to their owne wills, but then they rage and ſwell. He is a wiſe man, which can tell in what breſt truth of affection lyeth and that can weigh out to himſelfe a dramme of unfeigned friendſhip for generally men can pronounce all their Friends with a breath,<note place="margin">Circuitu unguis.</note> and write all their Friends (as that wiſe man ſaid) within the compaſſe of a nayle. Oh theſe lippes of ours ſpeake a great deale of falſe Engliſh, theſe armes of ours give many falſe embraces, theſe browes of ours have many falſe ſmiles hanging upon them; if the Friend be common what is the reaſon that peeviſhneſſe and policy, and perfidiouſneſſe are ſo common? if the Friend be common, why are ſuits, and ſpights ſo common? From whence come theſe tares?<note place="margin">Vnde-haec Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zania? <hi>Matt. 13.27.</hi>
                  </note> from whence come theſe diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? If the world be at peace, why are there ſo many Jave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins, and Speares, Sacres, and Demiculverins, I meane ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unkindneſſes, and ſhrewd turnes? doubtleſſe theſe things ſhew the flagge of defiance hung out this is the drawing age, men fight at ſharpe.<note place="margin">Armati coeunt in vulniera fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres.</note> 
                  <hi>Brethren meet for wounds</hi> there is bicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, as in a pitched field. But oh beloved, why abuſe ye neighbourhood? why make ye life a torment? chide out the friend?<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.22.</note> frowne out the friend? no, <hi>love one another with a pure heart fervently.</hi> Be not thou of a diſcourteous, much leſſe of a vexatious diſpoſition, but uſe the world gently, give it a taſte of thy good nature, <hi>Be a Friend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But further a Friend,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Doct.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe helpfull, for this party was a great Feaſt-maker. From hence obſerve, that the helpfull hand is the true tryall of Friendſhip, hee that never parteth with any thing, we account but a cloſe Friend. A man may know whether the Friend dwelleth at thy houſe,<note place="margin">Si proximus non extit vacuo ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu. <hi>Amb.</hi>
                  </note> namely if thy poore neighbour goeth not over thy threſhold with an
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94287:8"/>empty boſome. He is not a Friend, which maketh himſelfe the ſole Owner of his eſtate, uſe for thy neceſſity,<note place="margin">Vtere neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, da ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, <hi>Aug.</hi> Quicquid ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria ſubtrahis, tribuae eſurienti. <hi>Naz. orat. de paup. amandis.</hi>
                  </note> but give of thy ſuperfluity. Whatſoever thou ſpareſt from thine owne belly, diſtribute to the needy. He is reall with the world, that turneth Benefactour, which hath his ſpread table to witneſſe his affection, when a man may ſmell out the Friend in a Cooke roome, and get a taſte of him in his meſſes, whoſe almeſdeeds are the pawnes of his affection, and the ſeales of his friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Therefore the Apoſtle being to teach the world the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Friend, ſaith, <hi>Be ready to diſtribute, ſow liberally,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17. 2 Cor. 9.6. Rom. 12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>bee given to hoſpitality.</hi> This ſame hoſpitality is a better argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy friendſhip, then a hundred congies, and cringings. He loveth the world, that feedeth the world; not which fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the ears of it with diſcourſe, but the bowels of it with dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the worlds great Friend, is a great Houſe-keeper. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iob</hi> eateth not his morſels alone.<note place="margin">Ioh 31.7. Gen. 18.1.5. Neh. 17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> ſitteth at his tent dore to invite ſtrangers, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> prepareth Oxen and Sheep, and Fowles, and Wine in abundance; this is ſerious affection, theſe are the worlds faſt Friends.</p>
               <p>The uſe of this ſerves to reprove the hungry affection, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>
                  </label> and ſtarved friendſhip of theſe times; the Friend is not known by the hand, no men are fettered to their eſtates.<note place="margin">Divitiis aligan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Cyp.</hi> Auram reſpicis, fratrem vero non aſpicis, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil. Ser. 1. in div. avar.</hi> Tu phaſianos, attagenas, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp; omnia volutilia coeli devoras, ſed quod pauperis repleat ventrem non largiris, <hi>Chryſ. hom. 10 de divite, &amp; paupere.</hi>
                  </note> Thou lookeſt onely upon thy cankring gold and not thy periſhing brother. Thou eateſt Pheſants, and Quailes, and Turtles, and thy mouth is a lover to receive all the fowles of heaven, but thou giveſt not fragments to the needy. There is an aboundance of complement in theſe dayes, but little nouriſhment; thou maiſt be a conſort, but no gueſt; thy friend may breake his mind to thee, but he will not breake his bread to thee; our affection reacheth not to belly cheere, friendſhip is not Cauldron-deep No, ſuch Friends we had once, which were knowne by the. Dreſſer, they provided a Carver for the Country, the chiefe furniture of their houſes was the preſence of neighbours, and the chiefe burniſhing of their roomes was hoſpitality, this they accounted better then ſtately chimney-peeces, curious hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, a goodly Balconey for Monſier to jet upon, or a rich Cabinet for Madam to lay up her powders, and complexion-waters,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94287:9"/>criſping-pinnes, and dentifrecis, civets and jewels. All the ambition of thoſe times was to get the long table fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, to have friends about them. Oh how did charity ride then in a triumphant Chariot, and bounty flow in a full ſtreame in this Nation! But theſe men have left the ground behind them, but no ſuch faire feet to tread after them, they are lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in another world, and a man would thinke they died childleſſe, ſo few of their true heires do we find amongſt us. Some I confeſſe there are, but they ſtand like Beauties in the midſt of ſteynings, they are not the Tenth to the full croppe, which we did once enjoy. For many amongſt us have magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent buildings, but they might be pulled down, for no Friend dwelleth in them; they feaſt none, or none but their kindred, and their new created conſanguinity, their Tenants, and their Work-men; if private reſpects doe not invite thee, thy trencher is not layd, thou ſhalt then be fed by the ſight of their gay clothes, and not by the taſt of their rich banquets, by looking upon their painted Portals, and not by taking up a ſeat at their garniſhed Tables. But oh! why doe ye profeſſe friendſhip to the world, and maintaine it with leane cheekes? no, provide diet for it, maintaine it full-fed. Therefore away with this ſaving humour, ſpare not more then is fit, but be a helpfull cheriſhing creature here below, Be <hi>a Friend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The relation Our, Our Friend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let us come to the relation <hi>Our.</hi> From hence obſerve, that <hi>we ought to prize a Friend according to our owne intereſt,</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> for though a man of a friendly nature in generall ought to be reſpected, yet the dearer reſpect ought to goe, where there is the neerer relation; oh theſe ſame relations carry great efficacy with them, we ſhould know the ty of a poſſeſſive, this ſame <hi>Noſter, Our (Our Friend)</hi> ſhould reflect ſtrongly upon us, it ſhould call us forth by name to witneſſe our particular reſpects.<note place="margin">1 Eſ.</note> 
                  <hi>The Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his Maſters cribbe,</hi> where men have received any food or nouriſhment, even for the cribbe and Mangers ſake they ſhould know their good Maſters. Worth ought to be acknowledged, eſpecially
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94287:9"/>of them, which have received the benefit of it; it is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for inhumanity, for the chiefe Butler not to know <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 40.23. 1 Sam. 25.10.</note> and for <hi>Nabal</hi> to ſay, <hi>Quis eſt David? quis eſt filius Iſhai? Who is this David? who is this ſonne of Iſhai?</hi> knew he him not, when he had defended his eſtate, and been a wall to him both by day and night. Benefits have a reſultancy of reſpect from all good natures; Can the Jewes for get their good Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion? no, they plead for him,<note place="margin">Luke 7.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee loveth our Nation, and hath built us a Synagogue.</hi> Can <hi>Naomi</hi> forget her <hi>Boaz?</hi> no, he remained a Friend, when all other Friends were carried into the land of forgetfulneſſe, therefore whoſoever is ſilent in his praiſes, ſhe will bleſſe him.<note place="margin">2 Ruth 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed be he of the Lord for he ceaſeth not to ſhew kindneſſe to the living, and to the dead.</hi> Can the widowes forget their <hi>Dorcas?</hi> no, they had a ſpeciall intereſt in her, therefore as others waſhed her, ſo they will bath her in teares, as others layd her ſorth, ſo they will lay her forth with honour, they ſhewed the coats and garments which <hi>Dorcas</hi> had made whilſt ſhe was living.<note place="margin">9. Acts 39.</note> How doleful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> lament the deaths of <hi>Valentinian</hi> and <hi>Gracian?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Velut oculos mihi defoſſos dolco. <hi>Amb. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Auneb. de ob.</hi> Valentiniani ſicut duo vitulo ſimul educati, &amp; ſub codem jugo aſſueti— lamentabili mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitu omnia com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plerent, <hi>Greg. Naz. Monod. de vitae &amp; morte Baz.</hi> Poſſum obliviſci tui cum quo ſemper vitae hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus aratra ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinui? <hi>Amb. orat. funebri de ob. Satyr.</hi> Vſe. Cantari dignus.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they have pleaſured me ſo often and were ſuch a countenance to my profeſſion, that I bewaile the loſſe of theſe two good Emperours, as if I had loſt my two eyes,</hi> Greg. Naz. ſpeaking of his <hi>Baſil,</hi> that they two being brought up like two heyfers under the ſame yoake, when they came to part, they filled all places with a lamentable bellowing. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaking of his deare brother <hi>Satyrus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Can I ever forget thee, with whom I have ſpent out my life in laying my hand to the ſame plow-beame?</hi> no, theſe ſame relations make holy men paſſionate, they ſpeake feelingly of their proper Friend as our Saviour here, <hi>Amicus noſter, Our Friend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The uſe ſerves to reprove them which know not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of an intereſt, friendſhip is not in her right predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in theſe dayes, we meet with few Relatives in this age. For though a man be <hi>worthy to be celebrated,</hi> yet they which have received the ſilvery ſhowre of his perfections, are not moiſtened at the root, with the apprehenſion of his worth, no, men are forgotten in the place where they have done good:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94287:10"/>for how many pariſhes which have been comforted, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the preſence of reverend,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.10. <hi>Geneva</hi> tranſl.</note> and famous men, yet even amongſt them the foot prints of their deſerts are worne out, and the memory of their excellencies is dried up? But oh know you your celebrating part, eſpecially when ye are prepared, and prompted to it by perſonall advantages. Reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liating is the bond of Nature,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſtor.</hi> Praestita dona numerantur, <hi>Caſſio.</hi>
                  </note> yea, its the juſtice of a gratefull ſpirit, when benefits are kept upon tale, when men are faithfull Accountants, and skilfull in this Arithmatique. Oh therefore let not your Friend eaſily depart out of your mind, becauſe he is Yours, becauſe ye have his friends tokens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, in your judgements, in your conſciences; ye have been the limbecks through which his heavenly doctrines have been diſtilled, ye have been the cruſes into which his ghoſtly counſels have been put, therefore whoſoever expungeth the memory of his worth, yet keep ye deepe impreſſions of it, for ye have an inward feeling of it, therefore call him by his right name, ſtile him, and eſteeme him no leſſe then a Friend, if he ſhould ſcarce be a neighbour to others, yet to you he muſt be a Friend, for <hi>Amicus noſter, Our Friend.</hi> But why doth Chriſt ſay, <hi>Our Friend?</hi> becauſe he was a Friend to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and a Friend to his Cauſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt a Friend to his perſon, for he had often feaſted Chriſt. From hence obſerve, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> that <hi>Charity is then in her eminency, when Chriſt is made the Gueſt;</hi> I meane when profeſſion hath the taſt of our bounty. For who deſerves love better then the Friends of Chriſt, thoſe which ſanctifie the ground where they tread, and bleſſe Nations? This is no dreſſe a dinner for the Church,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> and to put meat into the mouth of God. <hi>Doe good unto all, but eſpecially to the houſhold of faith;</hi> For mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring to the neceſſities of the Saints, is <hi>Charitas ordinata, Charity rightly ordered.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> The uſe of this ſerves to reprove the inconſiderate charity of theſe times, for how many are boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, yea, perhaps prodigall, but how little droppeth to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-wards? Chriſts want his Friend, his members look lanke, his little ones are not battened; for all the large expences that are amongſt us yet religion taſteth little of the delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94287:10"/>of the times, grace finds not the age much charged with her. But whatſoever ſhe ſpends upon others it is but for her fame,<note place="margin">Quicquid pro a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima tua feceris hoc tuum eſt, <hi>Chriſ. in Mat. 6.</hi>
                  </note> but whatſoever ſhe ſpends upon the Saints is for your conſciences, and that which thou doſt for thy ſoule is onely thine; Let them then be thy ſable fellows which thou lookeſt to have to be thy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs; that thou maiſt have ſome living Saint to pray for thee upon earth, that thou maiſt have ſome dying Saint to carry newes of thy charity into heaven, endear thy ſelf to God, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiate thy ſelf chiefly to Chriſt Jeſus, that there may be <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, &amp; Amicus noſter,</hi> A Friend, and Our Friend, becauſe a Friend to Chriſts perſon.</p>
               <p>Secondly a friend to his cauſe: from hence obſerve that religion ought to have a portion in our affections,<note place="margin">Doct. 2. Theſ. 2.10. Luke 19.27. Acts 5.39. Mat. 12.30.</note> for <hi>the love of Chriſt is the love of his truth, the reſt are accounted enemies and fighters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God. For he that is not with me is againſt me.</hi> We ought therefore to be printed Chriſts, as <hi>Ignatius</hi> was ſaid to have the name of Chriſt written in his heart in golden Letters;<note place="margin">Aurcis literis. Stricto enſe <hi>Plut.</hi>
                  </note> yea as <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio</hi> ſware all his ſouldiers upon the edge of a naked ſword to the State of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo we ſhould all be ſworn to profeſſion. Can any man endure to have his cauſe forſaken? no, he that will not inſiſt in that his love is ſuſpected, and he will never be owned as a friend. Chriſt liketh a feaſt well, and will accept of a feaſt, but it is not a feaſt, that will perfect friendſhip, no, the Phariſees often feaſted Chriſt, and they were but Charger-friends; therefore the main thing is to cloſe with Chriſt in profeſſion, and to ſtand firm to him in point of honour, they are ſaid to receive Chriſt who receive his teſtimony,<note place="margin">Acts 22.18.</note> that is thoſe that ſubſcribe to Chriſts cauſe, and enter plea for him.<note place="margin">Heb. 2.10.</note> Chriſt is called the Prince of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and wherefore? to ſignifie that there is ſome allegeance to be taken of us, and what greater then to maintain Chriſts crown, and dignity, thoſe are Chriſts loyall ſubjects which ſeek to enlarge Chriſts territorie, and will draw their ſwords for their Prince, to fight the good fight of faith,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.11.</note> which endeavour to make Chriſt great, and even walk with his princely robe upon his back, and to ſit in his imperiall throne, theſe are thoſe which are true to Chriſt, which are his faſt friends.</p>
               <p>The uſe of this ſerves to examine, whether we have a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94287:11"/>love glowing in our boſomes; no, Chriſt Jeſus is even friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, we are not much taken with our Prince his ſcepter-point the Kingdome of heaven ſuffers little violence, we do not gather parties and draw adherents to Chriſt; Chriſt is little the better for us, his friend: do not pleaſure him much, we do not furniſh his banquet, nor enter fellows into his ſervice to weare his livery, not bring men to repentance out of the ſnare of the Devill.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.26.</note> We plant no colonies, nor procure our Maſters feet to tread upon new territories; no, an outward league we are contented to maintain with Chriſt, a civill combination to uphold correſpondencies, but for Religion to proſper or decay, to flouriſh or languiſh, to keep life or to draw home, it is all one to us. But oh beloved, as <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerius</hi> was called <hi>Publicola</hi> for his love to the common-wealth, ſo we ſhould be called <hi>Chriſticolae</hi> for our faithfullneſſe to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cauſe,<note place="margin">Plutarch. 1 Cor. 16.22.</note> 
                  <hi>For if any man love not the Lord Jeſus</hi> (and what greater love, then in ſeeking to preſerve the purity of the faith, and endeavouring to propagate the faith?) <hi>let him be Anathema, Maranatha accurſed,</hi> that is bitterly accurſed; pitty it is, that thou ſhouldſt bear the name of Chriſt, if thou wilt not be a hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.9. Col. 4.11.</note> a work-fellow to the Kingdom of Chriſt. Oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be inward with Religion, deare to Chriſt, ſick of love to thy well beloved, juſtify his cauſe, vindicate it from reproaches, every way endeavour <hi>to have ſoules added to the church, to have numbers of beleevers turned unto the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.41. Act. 11.21.</note> for this is the cauſe of Chriſt, and they which love Chriſt, love his cauſe, look there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the diſpoſition, look to the relation, to be a friend and Chriſts friend, a friend to his cauſe, that it may be ſaid, <hi>Amicus Noſter.</hi> Our Friend.</p>
               <p>But why doth Chriſt ſay <hi>Amicus noſter</hi> Our friend, and not <hi>Amicus meus,</hi> my Friend? becauſe Chriſt was not contented to eſteem him a Friend himſelf, but he would have his diſciples to own him, he would draw them into the bands, and have a joynt reſpect ſhewed to him. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> From hence obſerve, that whom Chriſt loveth, we ſhould love alſo. He which doth ſervice to Chriſt the whole profeſſion is engaged to him; A righteous man ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours them that feare the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.5.</note> not onely honour the Lord, but honour them that feare the Lord, not onely honour the Maſter
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94287:11"/>but honour the ſervants; for as <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaid of <hi>Hepheſtion,</hi> This is alſo <hi>Alexander,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Et hic Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der eſt</hi> Plut. <hi>Deifici,</hi> Cypr. 1 Ioh. 5.1.</note> ſo this is alſo Gods; for godly men are particles of God, and God will be honoured in his particles. He that loveth him that begat, loveth him that is begotten alſo. Gods Friends muſt not walk up and down as if they had none but their maſter to take them by the hand, but the whole fraternity muſt acknowledge them, for all my delight is in the Saints,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.3.</note> and ſuch as excell in vertue; we ſhould bleſse their expreſſions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire their acquaintance; if they be Chriſts, they ſhould be ours.</p>
               <p>The uſe of this ſerves to reprove them, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> which leave Chriſts friends to himſelf, for generally none are acknowledged but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on particular reſpects; if they have pleaſured us, then are we boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to them, we are at their diſpoſe, we are their ſervants, but religion carries no ſuch ſtrict obligation with it, Chriſts relation is none of ours, for let a man be never ſo rarely gifted, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly endowed, the very reflex of Gods face, the print of his purity yet for his meere ſanctity he is lightly reſpected, precious he may be in Gods eye, but man hath no eye for him, or it is a very ſupercilious one; but oh! true friendſhip, is for Gods ſake, for a good man <hi>will love in man nothing but God,</hi> that is the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his grace, and how can the heart here be divided? no it is coupled together with Chriſts glew. Therefore Let God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend friends to us,<note place="margin">Non amabit in homine niſi De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. <hi>Aug.</hi> Chriſti glutino copulatur <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> if they bring along with them his certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate, that is, the fruits of his Spirit for their Maſters ſake, let them be entertaind; if the Court hath beſtowed honours upon them; and created them noble, let us give them their titles, yea, carry ardent affection to them, for religion is the foulder of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Let us acknowledge the King in his image, God in his ſaint, for he is Gods, therefore let him be ours,<note place="margin">Ferrumen ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum <hi>Naz.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Noſter Amicus</hi> Our Friend,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2 Part.</head>
               <p>Now let us come to the name <hi>Lazarus, Lazarus,</hi> that was happy in eſtate, happy in a priviledge, happy in his kindred.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:94287:12"/>
               <p>Firſt happy in eſtate, for <hi>Bethany</hi> was his towne, and he dwelt at the Caſtle. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> From hence obſerve that riches are no impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment unto grace, God may have Caſtle guard in his tenure; if men do not love their riches, be not proud of their r ches, do not truſt in their riches, riches are no inconveniency for a ſtate of grace; for ſuch are looſe of the creature, and ſo may go freely unto God, yea the ſenſe of bounty oftentimes inſtilleth the ſenſe of duty, &amp; they ſerve the more readily, becauſe they are ſo richly hired, their preſent portion may cauſe them to chuſe the Lord for their portion, the comfort they find in theſe riches may make them ſeek for durable riches,<note place="margin">Prov. 8.18.</note> God ſuffers them not to want that which is his, and thy will not ſuffer God to want that which is theirs; he cauſeth all things to abound to them, and therefore they will not endure him to be ſcanted; the rich are not ſo unhappy, but they may truſt in the living God.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The rich and the poore meet together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Lord is the maker of them both.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 22.2.</note> Seing then he is a common maker, his fingers have left no curſe upon either, they are kept aſunder by ſome diſtance upon earth,<note place="margin">Hoc attendite ne paſſim divites reprehendatis. <hi>Aug.</hi> Non qui habet divitias ſed qui cuſtodit. <hi>Ier.</hi> Sufficientiam rerum non inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>center vult, quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis cum vult. <hi>Aug.</hi> Adſumenta vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum, <hi>Diſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar Ettim. Vſe.</hi>
                  </note> yet they may both meet in heaven.</p>
               <p>Take heed how ye reprove rich men hand over head, for not he which hath riches, but he that keepeth them, is to be blamed. Whoſoever deſireth it ſufficiently, deſireth it (if there be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſiniſter ends) lawfully, riches righty uſed are furtherances unto vertue. The uſe of this ſerves to reprove them, which abuſe Gods bleſſings; Oh that any man ſhould be damned by riches, yea that any man ſhould not be ſaved by riches, for wherefore is there a price in the hand of a foole to get wiſdome (that is grace) and he hath no heart unto it? it is not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of riches which do the hurt, but the want of a heart, not the liberall fortune, which brings the miſchief, but the miſerable fool; riches are no manicles on the hand, but a price in the hand; he guides a ſhip ill<note place="margin">Pro. 17.16. Pro. 10.15. Iames 4.3. Prov. 3.9. 1 Tim 6.19. <hi>Subſidium, non pondus ſunt. Greg.</hi>
                  </note> that ſinks by it. Order thy riches well there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, make them not thy ſtrong confidence, conſume them not on thy luſts, but honour the Lord with thy riches, lay up by them a good foundation againſt the time to come, and thy riches are not thy bane, but thy benefit; they are thy daily remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Gods favour, and the high, lofty where thou maiſt ſee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94287:12"/>Gods greatneſſe, and goodneſſe ſhining the more brighty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thee. Thou maiſt pray for all thy riches, and repent for all thy riches, and bring forth fruit unto God for all thy ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; Riches hinder not the motions of the ſpirit, nor inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of grace. Thou maiſt be wealthy therefore, and for all this happy, for remember <hi>Lazarus</hi> the rich.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Lazarus,</hi> happy in a priviledge,<note place="margin">Io. 11.4.</note> for This ſickneſſe is not unto death, but unto Gods glory, <hi>Lazarus</hi> was ſicke, but not curſe-ſicke, but a I may ſay glory-ſicke. Sick he was, but he ſhould fall into the hands of a good Phyſician, who would have credit of his Patient honour of his Cure, the iſſue ſhould be glory. From hence obſerve, that the ſaints miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, end in Gods glory. No marvell, that God ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> Deut. 32.3.</note> that all his Saints are in his hands, for who can but wonder that cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſhould turne felicity, and affliction advantage, if the ſaints in theſe things were not in the hands of God? but this is Gods workmanſhip, his Divine art the skill of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, thus can the hands of God order things, that at laſt there is nothing to be ſeen upon them but characters of glory. A godly man by them is not preſſed downe, but lifteth up;<note place="margin">Non premitur ſed levatur, <hi>Aug. ep. 45.</hi> Optimum genus gloriae, <hi>Bern. l. 2. Conſ. c. 6.</hi>
                  </note> yea, affliction to the Saint is the beſt kind of glory. All things ſhall worke together for the beſt of them which love God <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. All things even the worſt things; all things even wretched things; let them worke and ye ſhall ſee them work kindly; God, and miſery will at laſt worke a ſtrange worke, though they worke not by themſelves, yet they worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not to teares, but to triumph; not to confuſion, but to admiration to what can be deſired to more then can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to the beſt; God will have the beſt out of the worſt, if people love God; he will have his love-markes ſeene upon them though they begin in ſorrow, or ſhame, yet they ſhall end in glory. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> got an Iron chaine of his heele (but oh the glory I) at laſt it ends in a golden chaine about his necke; <hi>Moſes</hi> is caſt into an Arke of Bull-ruſhes (but oh the glory!) at laſt he is laid in the lappe of a Princeſſe; <hi>Jonas</hi> is caſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board (but oh the glory!) he is ſoon ſhipt into a new barge, a Whales belly, and after he hath been three dayes, and three
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94287:13"/>nights Sea-ſick, the crare ſhal turn the Prow to land, and ſet <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> ſafely on ſhore. <hi>Daniel</hi> droppeth into a Lions den (but oh the glory!) not into the Lions jawes, no, the Lions are his Keepers, his ſtrong guard; the Lions at Court would not ſpare him, the Lions in the denne would not touch him; no, the Lions and <hi>Daniel</hi> are Chamber-fellows, Bed-fellowes; if <hi>Daniel</hi> will take up a nights lodging with the Lions, hee ſhall be as ſafe in their denne, as ever hee was in his owne chamber.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> The uſe of this ſerves to ſhew the happineſſe of the Saints, their happineſſe in unhappineſſe. He which lappeth in Gods boſome, what need he feare?<note place="margin">In ſinu Dei poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, quid poteſt timere, <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> no happen what will, he cannot be ſhaken out of Gods boſome the rack of the world may for a while terrifie him, but the ſight of Gods boſome ſoone pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth him, for the Saints riſe up at laſt gayners by all their afflictions. <hi>He knoweth my way and trieth me and I ſhall come forth as gold;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 23.10.</note> Afflictions are Gods melting veſſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and the Saints never looke ſo well as when they come out of the fining pot, miſery ſets a kind of brightneſſe upon them they looke as purely at laſt, as the tried gold. God will have glory in us, not onely in our welfare, but in our extremities. Out of the <hi>eater</hi> there comes meat; the burning of the buſh is a flame of aſtoniſhment, yea a blaze of honour. As the Pomander being chafed, it giveth the better ſent, ſo a ſmell comes from the Saints by their adverſities; they are diſtreſſed for a while, but in concluſion they are made future wonders, everlaſting mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, ſpectacles of glory; The Saints miſeries end in glory. This ſickneſſe is not unto death, but unto Gods glory, <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> happy in a priviledge.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Lazarus</hi> happy in his kindred;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3. V. 5.</hi> Doct. Nil prodeſt ſi moribus diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes una habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione jungan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Rubar.</hi>
                  </note> for as he was religious ſo they were vertuous. Jeſus loveth <hi>Martha Mary,</hi> and <hi>Lazarus.</hi> From hence obſerve that it is a great bleſſing to have a ſanctified kindred, it profiteth nothing, if men dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in manners, though they be joyned together in the ſame family; no, this is like a godly picture, where the Graces are wanting, as <hi>Apelles</hi> ſaid of the peece of <hi>Protogenes;</hi> therefore that is felicity, where all are drawing in the ſame yoake, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94287:13"/>ſubſcribing to the ſame God, that there is not a loſt ſheepe in the whole flocke, nor a rotten cluſter hanging on the whole Vine, but every one waiting on the ſame Maſter, and devoted to the ſame Saviour; civill unity amongſt brethren is excellent, how much more unity in the ſame faith? it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for kindred to be proſperous alike, how much more to be gracious alike that as they are partakers of the ſame patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, ſo likewiſe they are partakers of the ſame promiſes? It was a griefe to <hi>Dives</hi> in Hell,<note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> that any of his brethren ſhould not goe to Heaven, ſo it might be a griefe to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of <hi>Dives</hi> upon earth, that they ſhould have a brother lying in hell.<note place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Rebeckah</hi> was troubled that the children ſtrove in her wombe; ſo a trouble may it be to any, that there ſhould be a repugnancy of qualites amongſt them, which come out of the ſame wombe. It was honour therfore to the elect Lady,<note place="margin">2. Ep. Iohn 4.</note> that all her children walked in the truth, and to <hi>Moſes Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam,</hi> that generally they did conſpire together in the ſame holy deſires. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> The uſe of this ſerves to exhort all kindred to ſtrive for this happineſſe, to apply themſelves to the like reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious duties to have this blood warme at the heart, to hold this knot of affection; for a pitifull thing it is, where the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is at his prayers, and the ſiſter at her dalliances; or the ſiſter at her mortifying exerciſes, and the brother at his riots; For, oh that the brother ſhould ſay, I tremble at the unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate eſtate of my ſiſter, or the ſiſter ſhould ſay, what ſhall become of the ſoule of my brother? Here is a troubled Sea,<note place="margin">Mare concuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
                  </note> oh ſuch ſit penſively to thinke that nature hath not ſo firmely united them, but after all ſmiles embraces, brotherly, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterly courteſies, Domeſday will part them; one muſt goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the bleſſed quire in heaven, the other muſt weepe, and gnaſh the teeth in hell. Therefore if deſires, or endeavours, counſell or reproofe, bending of knees, or ſhedding of teares, can inſtill the ſame affections, let them not be wanting, for it is a great happineſſe for brethren and ſiſters to goe hand in hand to the ſame God, as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was happy in his kindred; happy in his eſtate, happy in a priviledge, happy in his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Thus much for the name <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:94287:14"/>
               <head>3. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Now let us come to the accident <hi>Sleepeth.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> From hence obſerve, that <hi>Death</hi> is the let of the beſt, <hi>Lazarus</hi> is caſt upon Natures couch,<note place="margin">3. Eccleſ. 10.</note> and what Saint muſt not goe to be with him? yes, all go to one place. All, this All is Saint-numerall, yer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues bright peeces are ciphered out to the Dormitory the ſleeping roome.<note place="margin">9. Iob 22.</note> 
                  <hi>God deſtroyeth the perfect with the wicked.</hi> The perfect is imperfect, he may have a little the purer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but not a whit the purer materials; his conſcience may be the more renewed, but his conſtitution is not the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, they of the beſt houſe ſtand but upon a weake pinning. <hi>The wiſe die as well as the fooliſh.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 49.10.</note> Even they which were ſo wiſe as to ſhun the corruptions of the world yet they cannot ſhun the coru tion of Nature, though they have the wiſdome from above yet they have the fari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty from beneath.<note place="margin">1. Zach. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers where are they? and do the Prophets live for ever?</hi> No, the pureſt gold in our treaſury, is of cancred nature, the ſweeteſt flowre in our garden is but a ſearing herbe, theſe goodly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of divine perfections <hi>Mecay Gregory</hi> 3. deſerved well of God and men yet he died.<note place="margin">Monumenta fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſcunt. Bene meritus eſt de deo, &amp; homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, ſed mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus eſt, <hi>Plat. in Greg. 3.</hi> Legimus ſanstos plenos gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum plenos vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum migraſſe, <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  </note> We read that the Saints full of graces, full of vertues departed. St. <hi>Paul</hi> brings in a Catalogue of Saints <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. but to me it is but as a buriall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bill; for thoſe which obtained witneſſe that they were righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and had this teſtimony that they pleaſed God, which would not enjoy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon, but wrought righteouſneſſe, which were ſo matchleſſe, and prize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that this world was not worthy of them yet I find in theſe primer Worthies, ſome of natures ſetlings, Deaths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droppings, they ſcaped away to their graves they were locked up, but in periſhing ſinnes, people embraced in them but armfulls of rottenneſſe, they had their Writ of removall they were plucked from the upper ſtory to goe live in the vault, Natures purſivant fetched them away from us, Deaths Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine led them to bed, they all ſlept, <hi>Our friend Lazarus ſleepeth.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> The uſe of this ſerves to exhort you all to endure the Saints deaths with patience for why ſhould we be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94287:14"/>at a common lot? if ſuch a thing happened to them as never man endured, it were another matter. but when all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous men that ever lived before them drew this blanke, when nature hath no other Lottery, why ſhould they be diſquieted? It is well that they have lived ſo long as to deſerve well of the world to purchaſe to their ſelves the names of Friends, that they lent out their vertues before hand and have the age in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to them, that they have honoured their Callings, and honoured their Families, but that they ſhould live ever is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Natures Covenant, or any divine grant; though they have many priviledges, yet they have not this in their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Let it ſuffice therefore, that they have not loſt their graces, or loſt their ſoules, but onely a fraile life, a life that was never given them long to enjoy: Part therefore with ſuch, with an humble ſubmiſſion to Gods pleaſure, ſeeing thou letteſt them but go to be Bed-fellowes with the Saints, for all Saints ſtep into this couch <hi>Our friend Lazarus ſleepeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But why is death here called a ſleepe?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, becauſe it comes upon us unexpectedly, for ſleep doth creep upon us, and ſteale into the ey, men are aſleepe often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times before they felt any drowſineſſe about them even as they ſit, and talke, divers times they fall aſleepe; So Death comes oftentimes unlooked for we are ſnoring in our graves before we dreamt of bed time; <hi>The number of all our days are with thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">14 Iob 5.</note> They are upon tale, and God only knew the number of them; thou which haſt a months-mind to this life, thou maiſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in thy account, thou keepeſt no very good Almanacke about it, before the next new Moone come to the full, thou maiſt be in thy wane. <hi>No man knoweth his end;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">9 Eccl. 12.</note> no this ſame end is of ſuch a doubtfull nature, that the wifeſt cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve of it. <hi>I know not the day of my death ſaith Iſaac.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 27.1.</note> Wee may have skill in many things, but wee have no skill in the death-point no this were</p>
               <q>— Cauſas penitus tentare latentes.</q>
               <p>to buſie our wits about hidden cauſes, theſe are the ſecrets of Nature.<note place="margin">Abdita natura.</note>
               </p>
               <q>Naiades ignorant, ignorat &amp; Inachus ipſe,</q>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:94287:15"/>
               <p>The pureſt and the prudenteſt are hert to ſeeke we are not ſo much as morrow read,<note place="margin">James 4.14.</note> for <hi>We know not what ſhall be tomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi> A morrow there will be, but whether out morrow or no, it's uncertaine; ſomething there will be but whether death or life we cannot determine; No, we are deepe ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers till death come to examine as but ſhe ever poſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us in an Adverbe of time, and a future verſe.<note place="margin">Cras &amp; quid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls?</note> Oh then that men put ſuch confidence in life, which lookes ſo quick-ſighted, as if they had rubbed all ſleepe out of their eyes, as if it were a long time before they ſhould go to reſt. For art thou ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thinkeſt thou yet with a Deaths call? No, — <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thou ſaiſt with old withered <hi>Galba</hi> ſtill mee thinkes my ſprightly vigour remaines within me; ſuch mens ſpirits decay not, they feele not a ſymptome of death about them; people thinke they may take their owne time of ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, dy when they lift, howſoever they looke for ſome warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome hint of death; they thinke they ſhall not dy in their ſuites, they ſhall live to pay home ſuch an adverſary; they ſhall not dy at their bowſing-bowles, they ſhall live out ſuch a joviall meeting; they ſhall not dy in the midſt of their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes they ſhall locke ſuch a neighbour out of doores, chaſe ſuch an heire out of his burrow, his muſe firſt; Dy they ſhall, but they ſhall not dy yet.<note place="margin">Ex infidiis ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus, <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  </note> But on beloved this ſame death workes by ſtratageme her ambuſtment breakes out, and her mine ſprings before perſons ever dreame of an enemy. None have a more dangerous life then they which preſume of life: None dy more wretohedly, then they which thinke to dy at leiſure. Oh therefore well tempered health, ſtrength of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, let mee ſend the Sepulchre fray to your doores, the deaths-dread to your hearts, for the laſty Gallant is not ſo puiſſant, but he may be inſtandy caſt on his backe the miracle of beauty hath not ſuch amiable cheekes, but that ſhe may ere long looke carkaſſe griſly: Oh thinke upon <hi>Herod,</hi> who was ſtrooke from heaven, whilſt the people were deifying him, and marke <hi>Jeſabel,</hi> who had her braines daſhed out whilſt ſhe looked out at the window as the Paragon of beauty; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> which went downe quicke
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94287:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>into their graves, whilſt they were priding their ſelves in their gifts; and endowments; Oh therefere give over your thoughts of this world con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not with a Witch, that old witch of fleſh and bloud, but let God have thee to day leſt Death have thee to morrow, for Death is aſleep and ſleepe commeth unexpectedly.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Death is aſleepe becauſe it doth ty up the ſenſes, for as in ſleepe a man doth neither ſee nor heare, nor taſte <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So there are no pleaſing objects to be preſented to dead men, for hath Death any reſervation of comforts? no <hi>Wee are as water ſpiltupor the ground;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.14.</note> that were we never ſo firſt of cleere water, or ſiveet water yet the earthen pitchers will be turned upward and the moiſture of earthly contentments powred out. <hi>Doth not their dignity goe along with them?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 4.21.</note> yes, ſuch is the indignity that death put upon us, that it will not leave us any dignity.<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.17. Eccleſ. 9.5.</note> We take nothing away with us when we dy, we are all as ſtript creatures. <hi>The dead know nothing at all;</hi> no, they are ſtrangers to thoſe things which were their daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creements. <hi>Mine ey ſhall not returne to ſee pleaſure;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 7.7.</note> we have done with pleaſure, when we have done with life; as the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine run away, when the houſe doth fall, ſo doe all the jovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſances of this life forſake us, when we drop into our graves; yea a Funerall doth drowne all earthly delights,<note place="margin">Vt naufragium ſubmergit mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
                  </note> even as ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack doth the rich merchandiſe. Oh then that people are ſo heart-deepe in worldly vanities, that they are generally ſo ſenſe-ſicke I to pleaſe the ſenſes to delight the ſenſes, this is that which we all aime at our Markets and Exchanges, our Ships, and our Shops our Stillaries, and our fruiteries, are all for the ſenſes; the ſenſes have their needle ſtitching, their ſpiceries ſeaſoning their ſhittle running in every corner; there is much planing and graving pruning and inoculating for the ſenſes; we fetch downe the fowles out of the sky, we take the bottome of the Sea ſlay the earth, and dig all the oare out of Mines for the ſenſes; Milleners, Mercers, Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrels, Stage-players, Perſumers Conſervers Feather-makers, are a I Tradeſmen to ſerve five Cuſtomers, the five ſenſes; or this whole world is but one entire Incorporation divided
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94287:16"/>into ſeverall companies for the ſenſes. But Oh beloved, are we not ſenſeleſſe in this doting upon the ſenſes? yet, ſenſeleſſe, and graceleſſe too, for God hath appointed us to ſeek for things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent, and what duration in thoſe thing? they do but ſlender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refreſh us,<note place="margin">Leviter refrige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, &amp; brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deficiunt <hi>Bern.</hi> Voluptatum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus tenaces, ut illae ſunt fuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>Amb.</hi>
                  </note> and are ſuddenly periſhed; we are very tenacious of them, but they quickly glide from us; they drop away like autumne leaves, and were off like a crimſon gloſſe, they go out like blaſing ſtarres, or looſe their light like twinkling gloworms, therefore let us ſtudy for our ſouls, and not for the ſenſes, for we have but a ſhort time to make uſe of the ſenſes, for when we dy, we are as perſons faln a ſleep, who have their ſenſes tyed up.</p>
               <p>Thirdly death is like unto a ſleep, becauſe as ſleep takes away all the ſorrows of labour, (for the ſleep of a labouring man is ſweet) ſo death takes away the irkſomneſſe of all wordly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments,<note place="margin">Eccles 5.12. <hi>Fuga laborum</hi> Naz. <hi>Depoſitio ſarci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae gravis.</hi> Aug. <hi>Aerumnarum requies.</hi> Saluſt. Gen. 15.15.</note> for what is death, but the flight of labours, the laying off of a heavy burden, the repoſe after troubles. When the laſt houre of the day is come, people leave working in the vineyard, when the maſter appears, the tasks are taken out of their hands and they are no longer talent-buſy. <hi>Abraham</hi> uſed double dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence a while, but at laſt, he goeth to his fathers in peace, no more afterward to be diſquieted. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dy in the Lord. they reſt from their laboure,</hi> a ſolemne and ſerious reſt is then proclaimed,<note place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> therefore <hi>Paul</hi> that had felt enough of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, and exigents of this life, <hi>deſires to be diſſolved,</hi> and the faithfull ſigh,<note place="margin">1 Phil. 23. 2. Cor. 5.4.</note> and are burthened to have mortality ſwallowed up for they know that the grave ſhould be unto them as Gods pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, to eaſe their a king temples, as his couch to relieve them. Peace ſhall come,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſ. 57.2.</hi> Non nobis erep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus es, ſed peri. culis, non nos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſiſti ſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruentium cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine caruiſti. <hi>Amb.</hi> orat. Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neb. De Sat.</note> they ſhall reſt in their beds every one that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth before him. Therfore ſaith <hi>Amb.</hi> of his brother <hi>Saterus, Thou art not taken away from us, but perills thov haſt not loſt us but art freed from the feare of future troubles.</hi> Oh then that we know not the ſweetneſſe of death, that we feare it, lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k pale at it, ſhunne it that we would beg a ſtay of it, that we would (if it were poſſible) buy it off, we would do any thing rather then ſtr p our ſelves for the grave, endure all the calamities upon earth, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then death, it is grief and anguiſh to us to ſtep into bed, but alas in the meane time we do not know it, conſider the nature of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94287:16"/>it, mark the iſſue of it,<note place="margin">Non eſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num morientis <hi>Paulin.</hi> in vita <hi>Amb.</hi>
                  </note> for it is no dammage to the dying as <hi>Amb.</hi> told <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igonus,</hi> unleſſe freedome be a dammage, if thou beeſt godly dy when thou wilt thou dieſt to comfort, we are never hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier then in death, yea never happy before death;<note place="margin">Non major fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas eſt, quam in morte, immo nulla felicitas ante mortem. <hi>Ier.</hi>
                  </note> then the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eles are taken off which did ſo pinch our wriſts, and the yoke ſlipt off, which did ſo chafe our necks; we have then given our laſt grone, and ſhed our laſt teares. Oh then how joyfull ought that paſſage to be which being diſpatcht there remaines no more care or grief, Oh therefore fear life, but feare not death;<note place="margin">Quam illud i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter jucundum eſſe debet, quo confecto nulla reliqua cura, nulla ſollicitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do futura ſit. <hi>Cicero 1 Tuſ. Queſt. Eccl. 8.8. Rev. 21.46.</hi>
                  </note> here thou maiſt be too ſecure, or elſe there thou canſt not be unhappy if ſinne do not hurt thee, death cannot; nay, let us but carry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward atonement, peace of conſcience into our graves, &amp; there will be no fearfull dreames to trouble us in our ſleep, Here every day hath its grief, but there is not a minute of anguiſh; here is a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection houſe, but there all the whips are taken off from our backs here we weep our ſelves half blind with the ſmart of infinite miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries but there <hi>all teares ſhall be wiped away from our eyes;</hi> hee we faint under inceſſant imployments, but there the labourer taketh his reſt, there we ſleep.</p>
               <p>Fourthly death is like unto a ſleep in reſpect of a reſurrection for as the ſleepy man riſeth from his couch, ſo the dead from their graves; though we be at our repoſe, yet we ſhall not quite ſleep out our eyes, remain buried in bed, no, he will draw open the curtains, pull off the clothes,<note place="margin">Mors non ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptura cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, ſed corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem corporis <hi>Amb.</hi>
                  </note> and make us look up again broad-waken; death doth not deſtroy the body, but the corruption of the body it is but, the diſſolution not the deſtruction of nature; no, the body, that ſweet companion of the ſoule ſhall again renew its fellowſhip.<note place="margin">Diſſolutio non deſtructio na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae. <hi>Anſelm.</hi> Dulcis animae ſocius. <hi>Athena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>For thou turneſt man to to destruction and ſayeſt come again ye children of men;</hi> they which ſleep in the duſt of the earth ſhall awaken, <hi>there is a reſurrection of the juſt,</hi> we think we are quite buried, and we are but put to bed. Oh then that we know not our dying hopes? the righteous hath hope in his death, when he ſuſpends his life,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.3. Dan. 12.3. Luke 14.14. Prov. 14.32.</note> he hath not ended his hopes: no, a g acious perſon, when he feeleth the malignan cy of a diſeaſe, when he ſeeth the impotency of phiſicall receipts when he perceiveth the death p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onges at his heart, when his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news ſhrink u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s bloud congealeth, his teeth ſet, when he is, ſtretching forth a dying hand to ſeale away all his eſtate to a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94287:17"/>warm cloth, when the ſoule-bell is ſet out, and watchers and winders are in his eye, when he apprehends ſenſibly, apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that dy he muſt, all this doth not terrify him; for though he hath a drowſie brain, and knoweth that he muſt go into natures black room, yea put his cold feet into that ſame unwarmed bed even a bed of clay, yet he well underſtandeth, that he ſhall but pull the clothes a little over him, cover his naked limmes, remove himſelf out of the noiſe of the world, to take a ſhort nap, and then he ſhall drowſe no longer, but ſtep out of his grave, even as a man at the leaſt call, ſteps out of bed: What matter then if we ſhould inſtantly put on our night-clothes, if this houre were our ſleeping houre, for though we turn to aſhes, we cannot turn to nothing; no, theſe aſhes of ours are ſacred, God is the keeper of our duſt, as out of duſt he firſt framed us, ſo out of duſt he ſhall again reſtore us; we ſhall meet with our old bodyes, and we ſhall meet with our old vertues, there ſhall be redintegration of nature, and grace, not a drop of contrition, a ſpark of devotion, a mite of charity ſhall be loſt, but all our good works, like old friends ſhall come again to viſit us at our return; we do not dy to periſh, but dy to prepare for a reſurrection, for as the ſleepy man riſeth out of his couch, ſo ſhall we out of our graves.</p>
               <p>So that beloved, the day of this life will not alwayes laſt, no, the ſhadows are ſtealing on the diall, the evening ſtar at laſt will appeare, ſleeping time will come. Oh let us be carefull to put a <hi>Lazarus</hi> into bed, to have this ſleep come into the eyes of one of Chriſts friends, ſo ſhall we ſleep in a perſumed bed, yea ſleep as it were in Gods withdrawing room, where our reſt ſhall be ſhort, and our wakening ſweet; we ſhall dy comfortably, riſe again joyouſly, and reigne gloriouſly, which that we may do the Lord grant for his mercies ſake <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94287:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
